Brecht, Arnold; Papers ger024
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Arnold Brecht Papers
1865-1974
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger024
14.67 cubic ft.
The Arnold Brecht Papers, 1865-1974, consist of 14.67 cu. ft. of materials and are primarily copies of original documents, letters and printed materials housed at the Bundesarchiv, Koblenz, Germany ( Bundesarchiv, Potsdamer Strasse 1, 56075 Koblenz, Germany or http://www.bundesarchiv.de/ ).
Biographical Sketch
Arnold Brecht was born in 1884 in Lübeck, Germany. After completing his university studies in Bonn, Berlin, Göttingen and Leipzig, he received his Doctor of Law degree from Leipzig in 1906. In 1910, Brecht's career turned to civil service. From 1910 to 1933, he served under seven Reich Chancellors and more than a dozen Reich and Prussian ministers, until he was formally dismissed from his position as acting state secretary by Hitler in 1933.
Upon the invitation of Alvin Johnson, Brecht emigrated to the U.S. in 1933 to become one of the initial members of the newly formed "University in Exile", the Graduate Faculty of Political and Social Science of the New School for Social Research in New York City. Brecht remained on the Faculty of the New School until his retirement in 1954, after which he continued to lecture as an Emeritus Professor of Political Science and Jurisprudence until 1963.
In addition to his teaching and lecturing, Brecht was also called upon to advise the United States Military (OMGUS - Office of Military Government for Germany) in the rebuilding of Germany after World War II, as well as serving as an Expert to the Secretary of the Army, and a lecturer in the Army Specialized Training Programs at City College, Harvard and Haverford Colleges.
Arnold Brecht's publications, dating from his law school years, encompass the areas of civil law, international relations, political science and theory, and political, constitutional and administrative problems of his day. His best-known work, Political Theory. The Foundations of Twentieth Century Political Thought, has been reprinted several times as well as translated into German, Portuguese and Spanish. Brecht's rich and influential life and career are detailed in his memoirs, published first in German in two volumes (Aus nächster Nähe and Mit der Kraft des Geistes) in 1966 and 1967 respectively, and later condensed and released in an English edition under the title The Political Education of Arnold Brecht in 1970. Brecht died while on a visit to Germany on September 11, 1977.
1884 January 26, born in Lübeck, Germany; father Ernst Walther Brecht, mother Marie (Weishaupt) Brecht.
1902 Completed his Abitur from the Gymnasium, Lübeck
1902-1905 Attended universities in Bonn, Berlin, Göttingen and Leipzig.
1905 Studied in France.
1905-1909 In-service training in Hannover province and Berlin.
1906 Awarded Dr. juris utriusque from the University of Leipzig.
1910 Completed state examinations. Judge in Lübeck.
1910-1917 Counsellor to the Reich Ministries of Justice.
1911-1913 Secretary of the Governmental Commission for the Reform of the Penal Code.
1914-1917 Judge in Berlin.
1918 Counsellor to the Reich Ministry of Economics.
1918-1921 Counsellor to the Reich Chancellry; also Secretary of the Reich Cabinet
1919 Appointed Privy Counsellor.
1921-1927 Ministerial Director of the Reich Ministry of the Interior.
1927 Research on Public Administration in France and England.
1927-1933 Ministerial Director of the Prussian State Ministry and Finance Ministry. Representative of Prussia in German Reichsrat and rapporteur for federal budget. Vice-President of Reich Debt Commission. Member of the supervisory councils of the Reich Post Office and Federal Public Works. Lecturer in public law at the Hochschule für Politik. Vice-president, Institute for Economy, Public Administration.
1928-1930 Member, Reich Reform Commission.
1932 Leading representative and counsel for the Prussian government in procedure at Leipzig Supreme Court after the Papen coup.
1933 Emigrated to the U.S. to join the Graduate Faculty of the New School for Social Research, NY.
1933-1963 Professor of Political Science, Jurisprudence and Public Finance, Graduate Faculty, New School for Social Research.
1937, 1940 Visiting lecturer on government at Harvard University, Spring terms.
1942-1945 Chairman of the Special Committee on Comparative Government, Public Administration Committee, Social Science Research Council.
1943-1944 Lecturer, Civil Affairs Training Schools, Harvard and Yale. Supervisor of the Army Specialized Training Program, German area, City College, NY; also lecturer at ASTP, Harvard, Bard, Haverford.
1944 Woodward lecturer, Yale University, Spring term.
1945-1950 Member, Research Council, Institute of World Affairs, New School for Social Research.
1946 Became U.S. citizen. Third Vice President, American Political Science Association and member of its Research Committee (1946- ).
1948 May -- Sept., Expert to Secretary of the Army and consultant to OMGUS.
1952, 1954 Guest professor at University of Heidelberg, Summer semester.
1953 Appointed ex post to Staatssekretär by the Bonn Government.
1954 Became Emeritus Professor at the New School, March 15.
1959 First publication of Political Theory. The Foundations of Twentieth Century Political Thought. Awarded Das Grosse Verdienstkreuz der Bundesrepublik Deutschland.
1960 Received the Woodrow Wilson Foundation Award for the best political science work of 1959 (Political Theory).
1964 Awarded honorary Doctor of Letters degree from the New School for Social Research, upon the occasion of his 80th birthday.
1970 Jan. 26, awarded Das Grosse Verdienstkreuz mit Stern. June 24, death of Clara Brecht.
1973 Sept. 25, presented the New School Graduate Faculty Founders Medal.
1974 Jan. 26, celebrated his 90th birthday.
1977 Sept. 11, died in Eutin/Schleswig-Holstein, while on a visit to Germany.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence in German and English with Otto Braun, Heinrich Bruning, Jürgen Fehling, Theodore Heuss, and others, 1933–1970; lectures, notes, and syllabi, 1934–1938; offprints; and manuscripts of published and unpublished works, 1950–1970. Brecht was a Prussian official who was dismissed after defying Hitler in the last free speech in the German parliament. He was a professor of political science, public finance, and international law at the New School for Social Research. His principal work was Political Theory (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1959). This manuscript group was photocopied by the University Libraries with Brecht's permission before the originals were sent to the Bundesarchiv, Koblenz, Germany.
The collection is divided into six series: 1) Biographical and autobiographical materials, family documents, 1865-1974; 2) Correspondence, 1905-1976; 3) Writings of Arnold Brecht, 1904-1976; 4) Course and lecture notes, notes and clippings on various lecture topics, 1935-1963; 5) Writings by others, 1939-1974; and 6) Collections of materials (primarily clippings) on topics of interest. The writings of Brecht (Series 3) have been further divided into two Sub-series: 1) Full-length (book) publications, 1906-1974; and 2) Essayistic and literary writings, 1904-1976.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into six series. 1) Biographical and autobiographical materials, family documents, 1865-1974; 2) Correspondence, 1905-1976; 3) Writings of Arnold Brecht, 1904-1976; 4) Course and lecture notes, notes and clippings on various lecture topics, 1935-1963; 5) Writings by others, 1939-1974; and 6) Collections of materials (primarily clippings) on topics of interest. The writings of Brecht (Series 3) have been further divided into two Sub-series: 1) Full-length (book) publications, 1906-1974; and 2) Essayistic and literary writings, 1904-1976.
Acquisition Information
The originals of the Brecht Papers are located in the Bundesarchiv, Koblenz, Germany (Bundesarchiv, Potsdamer Strasse 1, 56075 Koblenz, Germany or http://www.bundesarchiv.de/). This manuscript group was photocopied by the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, with Brecht's permission before the originals were sent to the Bundesarchiv. Some materials were copied in 1976 before his death. The remainder was completed during the winter of 1978-1979.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Public Servants; Political Science; Military and Armed Conflict; Political science -- Study and teaching.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees.; Law -- Study and teaching.; Brecht, Arnold, 1884-1977.; New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.: 1919-1997)
- Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Family Documents, 1865-1974; 1; 98 file folders
  Scope and Contents
  The materials in this series document Brecht's life and career, both in Germany before 1933, as well as after his arrival in the United States. This series contains a number of documents relating to Brecht's career as Counsellor in the Reich Ministries of Justice (1910-1917) and Economics (1918), and the Reich Chancellry (1918-1921), as well as Ministerial Director in the Reich Ministry of the Interior (1921-1927) and various other ministries including the Prussian State Ministry and Finance Ministry (1927-1933), until his final dismissal by Hitler in 1933. Also included in this series are materials related to Brecht's activities as Expert to the Secretary of the Army (1948), as well as materials pertaining to HICOG (High Commissioner for Germany).
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically
  - Weishaupt, Theodor (grandfather). Documents, 1865-1890 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 1)
  - Birth and baptismal certificates (Arnold Brecht, Clara Berg), 1877; 1884 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 2)
  - School documents, 1896-1901 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 3)
  - Student newspapers, 1898-1899 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 4)
  - Diary, entitled "In schöner Zeit", 1900 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 5)
  - Silver wedding anniversary celebration of Brecht's parents, 1902 June 11 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 6)
  - Materials pertaining to Brecht's legal studies, 1903-1910 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 7)
  - Personal letters and employment records, 1905-1918 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 8)
  - Employment records, Reichsjustizministerium (Reich Ministry of Justice), 1905-1925 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 9)
  - Teaching evaluations, 1906 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 10)
  - "System der Vertragshaftung", 1908 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 11)
    Reviews & correspondence.
  - Reich Ministry of Justice, 1910-1918 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 12)
    Notes, correspondence.
  - Reports and correspondence concerning Belgium, 1910-1918 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 13)
  - Marriage certificate, 1915 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 14)
  - Military documents, 1915-1917 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 15)
  - Propaganda campaign, 1917-1918 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 16)
  - World War I, treaties & correspondence, 1918 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 17)
  - Brecht's appointment to "Kaiserliche Regierungsrat", 1918 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 18)
  - Brecht's notes on Cabinet meetings, 1918 October 29-1918 October 30 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 19)
  - Brecht's notes on Cabinet meeting, 1918 November 2 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 20)
  - Reports on the November Revolution, 1918 November 9 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 21)
  - Press conferences of the Reich Chancellry, 1918-1919 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 22)
  - Vorgeschichte des Waffenstillstandes. Amtliche Urkunden, herausgegeben im Auftrage des Reichsministeriums von der Reichskanzlei. Printed copy, 1919 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 23)
  - Documents relating to Brecht's position at the Reich Chancellry, 1918-1921 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 24)
  - Materials relating to the Kapp-Putsch, 1920 March 13 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 25)
  - Correspondence relating to Brecht's leaving the Reich Chancellry, 1921 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 26)
  - "Aufzeichnung über meine Unterredung mit Polizeipräsident Pohner auf seinem Amtszimmer am Donnerstag, den 10. Februar 1921 in München..." Transcript prepared by Brecht, Undated (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 27)
  - Brecht's account of his work for the Reich Ministry of the Interior, 1921-1927 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 28)
  - Celebration in the Paulskirche, Frankfurt, 1923 May 18 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 29)
  - Last Will and Testament of Marie Brecht, 1925 February 1 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 30)
  - Record of trips to London and Paris, 1927 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 31)
  - Documents and correspondence pertaining to Brecht's dismissal from the Reichsministerium des Innern, 1927 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 32)
  - Official documents pertaining to service in the Staatsministerium and Reichsrat, 1927-1933 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 33)
  - Articles pertaining to Reichsreform, 1926-1931 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 34)
  - Brecht's speeches on Reichsreform, 1926-1931 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 35)
  - "Die Beschlüsse des Verfassungsausschusses der Länderkonferenz". Reports by Brecht, 1929-1930 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 36)
  - Newspaper clippings on Reichsreform, 1928 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 37)
  - "Verfassungsausschuß der Länderkonferenz" (record of the meeting of the Constitutional Committee of the Conference of States), 1930 June 20-1930 June 21 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 38)
  - "Gesetz über die Reichsreform". Brecht's comments, 1930-1932 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 39)
  - Correspondence and clippings pertaining to Reichsreform, 1932 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 40)
  - Correspondence concerning Brecht's first visit to U.S., 1933 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 41)
  - Correspondence concerning trip to California, 1939 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 42)
  - Programs of lectures, panel discussions, 1940-1950 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 43)
  - Brecht's correspondence (Erwin Widder, Ernst Günther Prüfs, Gerhard Schulz, Jürgen Bay) concerning Reichsreform, 1954-1965 (Box 1 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 44)
  - Blätter des Deutschlandbundes. Copies of publication, notes, 1931 February 6-1932 August 24 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 1)
  - Brecht's recommendations on unemployment situation in Germany, 1932 March (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 2)
  - Materials concerning von Papen's coup d'état, 1932 June (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 3)
    Including statement by Brecht.
  - Documents concerning Brecht's first dismissal by von Papen, 1932 July (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 4)
  - Prussia vs. Deutsches Reich trial. Documents and clippings, 1932 July 20 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 5)
  - Prussia vs. Deutsches Reich. Documents and proceedings, 1933 February 6 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 6)
  - Documents concerning Brecht's second dismissal, 1933 February (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 7)
  - Report of Brecht's final days at the Staatsministerium, 1933 March (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 8)
  - Brecht's report of his arrest, 1933 April 6 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 9)
  - Documents and correspondence concerning Brecht's third dismissal, 1933 August (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 10)
  - Printed materials and notes on the Hitler regime, 1933-1934 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 11)
  - Appointment to the Faculty of the New School for Social Research & departure from Germany, 1933 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 12)
  - Departure from Germany, 1933 November 9 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 13)
  - "Arriving in America". Printed version of Brecht's retrospective essay (1970), and notes, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 14)
  - "Our Life Story". Documents and correspondence, documenting Brecht's activities, ca. 1933-1954 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 15)
  - Transcripts of important letters received by Brecht, 1934; 1964 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 16)
  - Social Science Research Council, Committee on Comparative Administration, 1941-1945 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 17)
  - Army Specialized Training Courses, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 18)
    City College, 1942-1944; Harvard, 1944.
  - Brecht's work for Council for Democracy, 1943 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 19)
  - Reports on activities, 1942-1946 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 20)
  - Brecht's appointment by the City of Hamburg to the Executive Committee of the Bizonal Economic Council, 1947 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 21)
  - Correspondence and reports on Brecht's work in Germany as "Expert to the Secretary of the Army", 1948 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 22)
  - "Meine Mission in Deutschland 1948 als 'Expert to the Secretary of the Army'". Brecht's notes and reports, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 23)
  - Brecht's suggestions to the new German Constitution, 1948 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 24)
  - HICOG (High Commissioner for Germany). Correspondence, notes, reports, 1950 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 25)
  - Notes on trip to Washington, 1951 January (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 26)
  - Mission to Heidelberg, 1952 Summer (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 27)
  - Report and related correspondence, trip to Germany, 1952 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 28)
  - Correspondence concerning University of Heidelberg, 1954 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 29)
  - Hula, Erich. "Arnold Brecht's Contribution to Comparative Government and International Relations". Article written on the occasion of Brecht's 70th birthday, 1954 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 30)
  - Friedrich, C.J. "Arnold Brecht. Jurist and Political Theorist", 1954 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 31)
  - Fulbright Award, 1954-1955 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 32)
  - Correspondence relating to trip to Bonn, Germany, 1955 June (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 33)
  - Award of Das Grosse Verdienstkreuz des Verdienstordens der Bundesrepublik Deutschland, 1959 January 31 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 34)
  - Woodrow Wilson Foundation Award, 1960 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 35)
  - Poems dedicated to Brecht by Ernest Hocking, Herbert Bailey, 1961-1962 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 36)
  - 80th birthday honors, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 37)
  - Honorary degree, New School for Social Research, 1964 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 38)
  - Award of Das Grosse Verdienstkreuz mit Stern, 1970 January 26 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 39)
  - Death certificate of Clara Brecht, 1970 June 24 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 40)
  - Presentation of Graduate Faculty Founders Medal, 1973 September 25 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 41)
  - 90th birthday honors, 1974 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 42)
  - 90th birthday, press clippings, 1974 (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 43)
  - "Erinnerungen und Geschichte. Ein autobiographischer Versuch", Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 44)
    Notes to volume 1 of Brecht's autobiography.
  - "Ungedruckte Teile meines Lebenserinnerungen", Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 45)
    Various versions, including deleted sections of Brecht's autobiography.
  - "Aus nächster Nähe". Appendices, materials to autobiography, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 46)
  - Notes, title suggestions to English version of autobiography, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 47)
  - Biographical notes, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 48)
  - Curriculum vitae, various versions, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 49)
  - Lexicon entries, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 50)
  - Lists of publications, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 51)
  - Index cards of Brecht's publications, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 52)
  - Listing of Brecht's papers given to the Bundesarchiv, Koblenz, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 53)
  - Articles, clippings about Brecht, Undated (Box 2 (1-Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, Famil), Folder 54)
- Correspondence, 1905-1976; 2; 319 file folders